Guide to the Andrew Watt Warden Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Andrew Watt Warden papers
1886-1943
MS 1224
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
Diaries, correspondence, writings, clippings and approximately fifty photographs of family and friends of Andrew Watt Warden. Warden's correspondence with family and friends centers on his interest in social issues and on their responses to both world wars, particularly World War II.
Warden, Andrew Watt, 1866-1947
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Jack R. Crawford, 1949.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Andrew Watt Warden's papers date for the most part from the later part of his life. His correspondence consists largely of letters exchanged with family and friends, although there is also some business and general correspondence as well. A large proportion of the letters deal with Warden's interest in social issues and his attitudes and those of his correspondents to the two world wars, in particular World War II. Warden had relatives in Scotland, England, France, Argentina, Canada, and the United States, and a variety of viewpoints is expressed.
In addition to correspondence, there are three datebooks for 1939-1940 containing notes on Warden's reading, social activities, and addresses. A few poems, humorous essays and short plays, and essays on political and social issues are also preserved. The remaining papers consist of printed matter such as pamphlets and brochures on political and religious matters; memorabilia including Warden's birth certificate and passport; and over fifty photographs of family and friends, for the most part unidentified and undated, although some date from the 1800s. There are also several negatives, one of which is glass.
These papers were donated to Yale University in 1949 by Andrew W. Warden's niece, Mrs. Jack R. Crawford.
Biographical / Historical
ANDREW WATT WARDEN (1866-1947)
Born on November 21, 1866, in Edinburgh, Scotland, he was the son of William Warden, a merchant, and Elizabeth (Watt) Warden. He moved to the United States and became active in social work, working for many years at the Union Settlement in New York City and later at a school for problem children, Children's Village, in Dobbs Ferry, New York, before retiring in 1936. He died in 1947.
World War, 1939-1945; Canada; Europe; Great Britain; Diaries; Social workers; Warden, Andrew Watt, 1866-1947
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1907-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 13)
  - Diaries and notebook, 1939-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings, 1910-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 15 - 16)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pamphlets, brochures, and other printed matter, 1886, 1939-1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Documents and memorabilia, 1894, 1914-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1912, 1932-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notes about correspondents and Warden family members, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)